Society for the Study of Evolution Records 1944-present Mss.Ms.Coll.81
American Philosophical Society
Society for the Study of Evolution Records
1944-present
Mss.Ms.Coll.81
American Philosophical Society
79.0 Linear feet
Founded in 1946, the Society for the Study of Evolution is one of the principle organizations for the study of the evolutionary sciences. Its bimonthly journal, Evolution, publishes work of general interest to researchers in the range of evolutionary disciplines. The Records of the Society for the Study of Evolution are a growing collection that includes material on the organization and governance of the Society, its conferences, and its journal, Evolution. The largest series by far contains the editorial files for Evolution, documenting Ernst Mayr's early efforts to solicit material for the journal, but including the editors' complete files from the 1980s onward.
Society for the Study of Evolution.
Accruals note
Additions to the collection are expected on a regular basis.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The SSE Records came to the American Philosophical Society library in several accessions from both Ernst Mayr and the Society for the Study of Evolution in 1979, 1986 and 1991 and on.
Some material relating to the Society was removed from the Conference on Evolutionary Synthesis collection (B M451) and interfiled appropriately into these Archives (Ms. Coll. No. 81). All documents relocated to this collection may be identified by their accession number written on the document or folder.
Conditions Governing Access note
Access to letters of recommendation for applicants for the Dobzhansky Prize, for Ernst Mayr's AIBS Distinguished Servce Award and G. Ledyard Stebbins' National Medal of Science are closed to reseach until 25 years from the date of writing.
Editorial records for the journal Evolution are closed for forty years from the date of submission.
Arrangement note
The collection (1944-present, 79 linear feet) is divided into nine series.
Series I. Constitution and By-Laws 1946-1970 1 folder
Series II. Minutes 1946-1981 4 folders
Series III. Officers 1946-1985 1.5 linear feet
Series IV. Committees 1946-1985 0.5 linear feet
Series V. Evolution Editorial Records 1946-present 75 linear feet
Series VI. Conferences 1946-1986 1.5 linear feet
Series VII. History 1946-1985 0.5 linear feet
Series VIII. Membership 1939-1970 10 folders
Series IX. Affiliated Organizations 1947-1985 8 folders
Scope and Contents note
The Records of the Society for the Study of Evolution include material on the organization and governance of the Society, its conferences, and its journal, Evolution. The largest series by far contains the editorial files for Evolution, documenting Ernst Mayr's early efforts to solicit material for the journal, but including the editors' complete files from the 1990s onward. We expect regular additions to the collection.
Biographical/Historical note
During the annual meeting of the American Association for the Advancement of Science held in St. Louis in March 1946, 57 members of the Society for the Study of Speciation and the Committee on Common Problems of Genetics, Paleontology and Systematics of the National Research Council gathered in a session chaired by Alfred Emerson to discuss forming an organization devoted to the "dynamics of evolution." Founded as a permanent, independent body, the Society for the Study of Evolution elected its first slate of officers that March, and adopted its mission to "promote the study of organic evolution in all its aspects."
At the first annual meeting of the Society in December 1946, the membership rejected a proposal to assume control of the American Naturalist in favor of creating a new publication specifically devoted to research on questions of plant and animal evolution. With the assistance of a grant from the American Philosophical Society, the journal Evolution was launched in 1947 as a venue for research in paleontology, genetics, taxonomy, ecology, and anthropology, providing the first cross-disciplinary forum for the evolutionary sciences.
In his 1952 history of the SSE, Ernst Mayr stated that "the aims of the Society, through its journal and otherwise, reflect the conviction that the evolutionary approach will clarify many unsolved biological problems and will provide common goals and mutual comprehension among all the life sciences." Today, the Society has an estimated 2,500 members and continues to publish Evolution bimonthly.
Mayr, Ernst, 1904-2005; Creationism.; Editorial files; Evolution (Biology); Evolution (Biology)--Periodicals
- Series I. Constitution and By-laws, 1946-1970; 1 folder (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Printed and typewritten versions of the Society's constitution and By-laws. A few of the printed editions also include a list of members. Additionally, there is an incomplete "articles to incorporate" as a non-profit corporation in the state of Michigan.
  - Articles of incorporation, By-laws and Constitution, 1946-1970; 1 folder
- Series II. Minutes, 1946-1981; 4 folders (Box 1)
  Typed and handwritten minutes of meetings, including the Society's organizational meeting of March 30, 1946, and all business and Council meetings thereafter. When business and Council meeting minutes could not be separated, they are retained together. The last folder in this series contains agendas from both the business and Council meetings.
  - Organizational meeting, 1946; 1 folder
  - Council meeting, 1946-1981; 1 folder
  - Business meeting, 1946-1975; 1 folder
  - Agendas for council and business meetings, 1946-1981; 1 folder
- Series III. Officers, 1946-1986; 1.5 linear feet (Box 1-4)
  Correspondence and reports of the President, Secretary, Treasurer, Editor arid American Institute of Biological Sciences (AIBS) representative, with lists of officers and council members for 1946-1975 and 1979-1981. Elected to a three year term, the Secretary administered the Society's affairs and therefore handled the bulk of its correspondence. Records of transactions conducted by the Society are most likely to be found in the Secretary's correspondence, from discussion on the constitution and advice to aspiring biologists to the battles with Creationists and letters welcoming newly elected officers. The Secretary also reported annually to the Council. The correspondence of the President also includes some correspondence of the President elect, and some material of interest relative to Creationism.
  The Editor likewise reported to the Council at its annual meeting both the financial condition of Evolution and statistics regarding the manuscripts submitted for publication. Some correspondence of the Managing Editor is also located in this section.
  - List of officers and council members, 1946-1981; 1 folder
  - President's correspondence, 1947-1967; 1 folder
  - President's correspondence, 1970-1979; 1 folder
  - President's correspondence, 1980-1985; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1946; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1947; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1948; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1949; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1950-1958; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1960-1969; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1970; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1971; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1973; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1972; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1974; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1975; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1976; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1977; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1978; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1979 January-July; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1979 August-December; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1980; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1981; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1983; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1984; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1982; 1 folder
  - Secretary's correspondence and reports, 1985; 1 folder
  - Secretary's calendars, 1971-1974; 1 folder
  - Treasurer's correspondence, 1947-1985; 1 folder
  - Treasurer's reports, 1946-1981; 1 folder
  - Editor's correspondence, 1947-1966; 1 folder
  - Editor's correspondence, 1972-1979; 1 folder
  - Editor's correspondence, 1980-1985; 1 folder
  - Editor's reports, 1947-1982; 1 folder
  - AIBS representative, 1969-1983; 1 folder
- Series IV. Committees, 1946-1985; 1 folder (Box 4)
  Material relating to the Nominating Committee, including nominations, biographical sketches of the nominees, vote tallies and correspondence. Although a committee of the Society was never formed to discuss Evolutionary Monographs, the series also contains information about Leigh Van Valen's one-man quest to convince the Society to produce a second publication for works too long to be published in Evolution. The Education Committee concerned itself largely with the repeated attacks of Creationists on evolution in the 1960s-1980s.
  - Committee for Conferences on the Evolution of Behavior, 1955-1958; 1 folder
  - Committee for Selected Anthology of Papers on Mammalian Evolution, [1968]; 1 folder
  - [Committee on Evolution outside the dollar area], 1957; 1 folder
  - Committee to reduce costs of publication, etc., n. d.; 1 folder
  - Education Committee, 1966-1983; 1 folder
  - Education Committee - clippings, 1970-1981; 1 folder
  - Evolutionary Monographs, 1967-1981; 1 folder
  - Investment Committee, 1967-1968; 1 folder
  - Nominating Committee - ballots, 1946-1985; 1 folder
  - Nominating Committee - biographies and nominees, 1946-1984; 1 folder
  - Nominating Committee - correspondence, 1948-1984; 1 folder
  - Nominating Committee - CY's of nominees, n. d.; 1 folder
  - Nominating Committee - list of members, 1968-1973; 1 folder
  - Nominating Committee - nominations, 1951-1984; 1 folder
  - Nominating Committee - reports, 1948-1980; 1 folder
  - Nominating Committee - vote tallies, 1947-1984; 1 folder
  - T. Dobzhansky Prize, c. 1976-1981; 1 folder
- Series V. Evolution Editorial Records, 1946-present; 74 linear feet (Box 5-8)
  The bulk of the series is comprised of correspondence with authors and reviewers of Evolution, dating from Ernst Mayr's term as Editor to the present. Reviewers' comments and the Editor's correspondence with reviewers are filed under the author's name except when the name of the author is not known, in which case they are filed under the name of the reviewer. Several folders are quite complete, including the author's letter requesting that his or her manuscript be considered for publication, Mayr's acknowledgement of receipt of the manuscript, his letters to the reviewers (2 each), the reviewers' response, Mayr's letter informing the author of the decision, and the author's response to that decision. Only very rarely is the manuscript included.
  Mayr was tireless in his pursuit of articles for Evolution and corresponded with prospective authors over long periods of time in hopes of soliciting material for the new journal. Finally, the series also includes some general information about the journal, concentrated in the periods 1946-1950 and 1981-1985.
  General note
  Only files open to researchers are listed.
  - Agreement with American Philosophical Society, 1947; 1 folder
  - Author Correspondence, 1 folder
  - Abbott, R. Tucker, 1948-49; 1 folder
  - Aldrich, John W., 1947; 1 folder
  - Anderson, Edgar, 1947-49; 1 folder
  - Angel, J. Lawrence, 1948; 1 folder
  - Armstrong, John C., 1948-49; 1 folder
  - Aronson, Lester R., 1947-49; 1 folder
  - Axelrod, Daniel l., 1948; 1 folder
  - Babbell, Gary, 1 folder
    See: Selander, Robert
  - Babcock, E. B., 1949-1950; 1 folder
  - Bateman, A. J., 1949; 1 folder
  - Bates, Marston, 1947; 1 folder
  - Beecher, W. J., 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Berrill, N. J., 1950; 1 folder
  - Blair, Albert P., 1949; 1 folder
  - Blair, W. Frank, 1949-1950; 1 folder
  - Blum, Harold, 1948; 1 folder
  - Bogert, Charles M., 1949; 1 folder
  - Bragg, Arthur N., 1949; 1 folder
  - Breder, C. M. Jr., 1948; 1 folder
  - Brieger, F. G., 1950-1951; 1 folder
  - Brighton, A. G., 1948; 1 folder
  - Brown, W. J., 1948; 1 folder
  - Burma, Benjamin H., 1949; 1 folder
  - Buzzati-Traverso, Adirano, 1948; 1 folder
  - Cain, Stanley, 1948; 1 folder
  - Camp, W. H. (Red), 1947-1949; 1 folder
  - Carson, Hampton L., 1947-1950; 1 folder
  - Caspari, Ernst, 1949-1950; 1 folder
  - Cazier, M. A., 1947; 1 folder
  - Chace, Fenner Jr., 1948; 1 folder
  - Chatterjee, Ranajit C., 1975; 1 folder
  - Clark, Austin H., 1948; 1 folder
  - Clausen, Jens, 1947-1949; 1 folder
  - Clausen, Roy E., 1949; 1 folder
  - Clay, Theresa, 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Cloud, Preston, 1948; 1 folder
  - Colbert, Edwin H., 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Constance, Lincoln, 1949; 1 folder
  - Cooper, Kenneth W., 1948-1950; 1 folder
  - Cronquist, Arthur, 1949; 1 folder
  - Crosby, Jack L., 1949; 1 folder
  - Cross, J. C., 1949; 1 folder
  - Crow, James, 1949-50; 1 folder
  - da Cunha, Brito, 1949; 1 folder
  - Cushing, John, 1947-1948; 1 folder
  - Deevey, Edward S. Jr., 1948; 1 folder
  - Dempster, Everett R., 1948; 1 folder
  - Denison, 1947; 1 folder
  - Dethier, Vincent G., 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Dice, Lee R., 1949; 1 folder
  - Diedenhofen, U., 1 folder
    see: Torres, A. M.
  - Dobzhansky, Theodosius, 1947-1950; 1 folder
  - Edinger, Tilly, 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Elias, M. K., 1947-1950; 1 folder
  - Elliott, Fred, 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Epling, Carl, 1947-1950; 1 folder
  - Federer, Walter T., 1947; 1 folder
  - Ferris, G. F., 1948; 1 folder
  - Fisher, R. A., 1949; 1 folder
  - Flower, Rousseau H., 1948; 1 folder
  - Ford, E. B., 1947-1950; 1 folder
  - Fox, Richard M., 1947; 1 folder
  - Freeman, T. N., 1948; 1 folder
  - Friedmann, Herbert, 1948; 1 folder
  - Fulford, Margaret, 1951; 1 folder
  - Gates, R. Ruggles, 1949; 1 folder
  - Gause, G. F., 1947; 1 folder
  - Good, Ronald, 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Gordon, Frank S., 1948; 1 folder
  - Gordon, Kenneth, 1947; 1 folder
  - Gosline, William A., 1948; 1 folder
  - Gottlieb, Leslie D., 1972; 1 folder
  - Granick, Sam, 1950; 1 folder
  - Grant, Verne, 1948-1950; 1 folder
  - Gregorius, 1 folder
    See: Ziehe
  - Gregory, William K., 1948; 1 folder
  - Griffin, Donald R., 1948; 1 folder
  - Gunter, Gordon, 1949; 1 folder
  - Gustafsson, Ake, 1951; 1 folder
  - Hairston, Nelson G., 1948; 1 folder
  - Haldane, J. B. S., 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Happ, George B., 1947; 1 folder
  - Haskins, Caryl, 1948; 1 folder
  - Heiser, Charles B. Jr., 1947; 1 folder
  - Helwig, 1950; 1 folder
  - Herre, W., 1951; 1 folder
  - Hervey, Ralph J., 1947; 1 folder
  - Hibbard, C. W., 1947; 1 folder
  - Hiesey, W. M., 1947; 1 folder
  - Hooijer, D. A., 1949; 1 folder
  - Hooper, Emmet T., 1948; 1 folder
  - Hough, Jean, 1949; 1 folder
  - Hovanitz, William, 1947-1948; 1 folder
  - Howard, Hildegarde, 1947-1949; 1 folder
  - Hsu, T. C., 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Hubbell, T. H., 1948-1950; 1 folder
  - Hubbs, Carl L., 1946-1950; 1 folder
  - Hutchinson, G. Evelyn, 1950; 1 folder
  - Inger, RobertF., 1947; 1 folder
  - Ives, Philip T., 1947; 1 folder
  - Johnstone, I. M., 1 folder
    See: Torres, A. M.
  - Just, Theodor, 1947-1951; 1 folder
  - Katz, Louis N., 1948; 1 folder
  - Kennedy, Clarence, 1947; 1 folder
  - Kerr, Warwick E., 1949; 1 folder
  - Kiriakoff, Sergius A., 1948; 1 folder
  - Klauber, Laurence M., 1947; 1 folder
  - Knight, J. Brooks, 1949; 1 folder
  - Kramer, Gustav, 1949-1951; 1 folder
  - Lack, David, 1949-1949; 1 folder
  - Laven, H., 1951; 1 folder
  - Lerner, I. Michael, 1947; 1 folder
  - Levene, Howard, 1949; 1 folder
  - Lewis, Harlan, 1950-1951; 1 folder
  - Linsley, E. Gorton, 1949; 1 folder
  - Liu, 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Lowe, Charles H. Jr., 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Lundman, Bertil, 1948; 1 folder
  - Luria, Salvador, 1947; 1 folder
  - Lutz, Bertha, 1946-1951; 1 folder
  - MacArthur, John W., 1949; 1 folder
  - McGregor, J. H., 1949; 1 folder
  - McGrew, Paul O., 1947; 1 folder
  - Matthey, R., 1947-1948; 1 folder
  - Matzke, Edwin B., 1947; 1 folder
  - Mayr, Ernst, 1947-1950; 1 folder
  - Merrell, David J., 1947-1949; 1 folder
  - Michaelis, Peter, 1948; 1 folder
  - Michener, Charles, 1947-1949; 1 folder
  - Miller, A. K., 1949; 1 folder
  - Miller, Alden H., 1946-1948; 1 folder
  - Miller, Dwight D., 1947; 1 folder
  - Miller, Robert R., 1947-1950; 1 folder
  - Montagu, M. F. Ashley, 1948; 1 folder
  - Moody, Paul A., 1947-1949; 1 folder
  - Moore, John A., 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Moreau, R. E., 1948; 1 folder
  - Muller, H. J., 1948; 1 folder
  - Munroe, E. G., 1951; 1 folder
  - Newell, Norman, 1946-1949; 1 folder
  - Ownbey, Marion, 1949; 1 folder
  - Park, Thomas, 1947; 1 folder
  - Parker, H. W., 1949; 1 folder
  - Patterson, Bryan, 1947-1950; 1 folder
  - Patterson, J. T., 1947; 1 folder
  - Petersen, Bjorn, 1949; 1 folder
  - Peyer, B., 1950; 1 folder
  - Phelps, William H., 1949; 1 folder
  - Pickford, Grace, 1949; 1 folder
  - Pitelka, Frank A., 1950; 1 folder
  - Pittendrigh, Colin S., 1947-1949; 1 folder
  - Pope, Clifford, 1948; 1 folder
  - Rand, Austin L., 1948-1951; 1 folder
  - Raw, Frank, 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Reed, Sheldon C., 1947-1949; 1 folder
  - Rensch, B., 1948-1950; 1 folder
  - Rhoades, Marcus M., 1947; 1 folder
  - Rick, C. M., 1947; 1 folder
  - Ripley, S. Dillon, 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Roberts, Tilden W., 1949; 1 folder
  - Rodbard, Simon, 1948; 1 folder
  - Rollins, Reed C., 1949; 1 folder
  - Romer, Alfred S., 1947-1949; 1 folder
  - Schaeffer, Bobb, 1948-1951; 1 folder
  - Schmidt, Karl P., 1949; 1 folder
  - Schrader, Franz, 1947; 1 folder
  - Schultz, Adolph H., 1947-1949; 1 folder
  - Schultz, Jack, 1947; 1 folder
  - Selander, Robert, 1973; 1 folder
  - Shull, A. Franklin, 1947-1948; 1 folder
  - Simpson, George Gaylord, 1947-1950; 1 folder
  - Small, James, 1948; 1 folder
  - Smith, Hobart M., 1948; 1 folder
  - Smith, Stanley G., 1949; 1 folder
  - Solbrig, Otto T., 1971-1973; 1 folder
  - Sonneborn, Tracy M., 1949; 1 folder
  - Southern, H. N., 1948; 1 folder
  - Spencer, Warren P., 1947-1948; 1 folder
  - Spiess, Eliot B., 1949; 1 folder
  - Spieth, Herman T., 1949; 1 folder
  - Stadler, Lewis J., 1948; 1 folder
  - Stalker, Harrison D., 1947-1949; 1 folder
  - Stebbins, G. Ledyard Jr., 1948-1950; 1 folder
  - Stenzel, H. B., 1948-1949; 1 folder
  - Stirton, R. A., 1947-1949; 1 folder
  - Streisinger, George, 1947-1948; 1 folder
  - Teichert, Curt, 1948; 1 folder
  - Thomas, Edward S., 1950; 1 folder
  - Torres, A. M., 1974; 1 folder
  - Trautman, Milton B., 1947-1950; 1 folder
  - Traylor, Melvin A., 1949; 1 folder
  - Turrill, W. B., 1949; 1 folder
  - Voous, K. H., 1948; 1 folder
  - Wagner, Warren H., 1950-1951; 1 folder
  - Wallace, Bruce, 1949; 1 folder
  - Webb, Glenn R., 1947-1949; 1 folder
  - Weber, Hermann, 1949; 1 folder
  - Westoll, T. Stanley, 1949; 1 folder
  - Wheeler, Marshall R., 1949; 1 folder
  - White, Michael J. D., 1947-1949; 1 folder
  - Williams, E., 1948; 1 folder
  - Wood, Albert E., 1947; 1 folder
  - Wood, Horace E. 2nd, 1948; 1 folder
  - Woodson, Robert E. Jr., 1947; 1 folder
  - Wright, Sewall, 1948-1950; 1 folder
  - Zangerl, Rainer, 1948; 1 folder
  - Ziehe, n. d.; 1 folder
  - Zielinski, Quentin B., 1948; 1 folder
  - Zirkle, Conway, 1947; 1 folder
  - Zohary, M., 1949; 1 folder
  - Lists of Editorial Board Members and Associate Editors, 1947-1986; 1 folder
  - Promotional materials, c. 1947-1950; 1 folder
  - Requests to reprint articles from Evolution, 1964-1981; 1 folder
- Series VI. Conferences, 1946-1986; 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Administrative material, 1946-1949; 1 folder
  - Administrative material, 1950-1958; 1 folder
  - Administrative material, 1960-1967; 1 folder
  - Administrative material, 1970-1979; 1 folder
  - Administrative material, 1980-1986; 1 folder
  - Programs, 1946-1974; 1 folder
  - Questionnaire, [c. 1972]; 1 folder
- Series VII. Membership, 1946-1974 (Box 9)
  - Applications, 1946-1974, n. d.; 1 folder
  - List of members, 1946; 1 folder
  - List of members, 1947; 1 folder
  - List of members, 1948-1953; 1 folder
  - Statistics on growth in membership, [c. 1953]; 1 folder
- Series VIII. History, 1939-1970; 10 folders (Box 10)
  - Clippings announcing founding and first annual mtgs., 1946; 1 folder
  - Committee on Common Problems of Genetics, Paleontology and Systematics of the, 1 folder
  - National Research Council, 1949; 1 folder
  - Correspondence related to founding of SSE and Evolution, 1945-1946; 1 folder
  - Correspondence related to writing history of SSE, 1952-1966; 1 folder
  - History of SSE by Ernst Mayr, 1952; 1 folder
  - Objects of the SSS and membership list, [1940]; 1 folder
  - Signatures of "Founders of the Society for the Study of Evolution", 1 folder
  - Study of Evolution. Names Attending Speciation Group, St. Louis, March 30, 1946." (Produced for 25th Annual Meeting), 1970; 1 folder
  - SSS bibliography of genetics, 1939-1940; 1 folder
- Series IX. Affiliated Organizations, 1947-1985; 8 folders (Box 10)
  - AAAS correspondence, 1947-1981; 1 folder
  - American Association of Physical Anthropology, [c. 1949]; 1 folder
  - AIBS correspondence, 1948-1974; 1 folder
  - AIBS correspondence, 1975-1982; 1 folder
  - AIBS materials, 1974-1979, n. d.; 1 folder
  - BSCS newsletter, 1972-1973; 1 folder
  - Genetics Society of Israel, 1965; 1 folder
  - Science as a Way of Knowing, 1984-1985; 1 folder